Wylie Wong collection of May's Studio photographs and San Francisco Chinatown ephemera M1999
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Wylie Wong collection of May's Studio photographs and San Francisco Chinatown ephemera
circa 1920-2006
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Lee, Isabelle May
Wong, Wylie
Lee, Leo Chan
M1999
43 Linear Feet (10 manuscript boxes; 13 flat boxes; 9 oversize flat boxes; 27 map folders)
Photographs and negatives from May's Studio; also posters, artwork, and ephemera relating to theater, life, and culture in San Francisco's Chinatown, circa early-mid 20th century.
Access to Collection
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series:
Series 1. Photographs
Series 2. Glass-Plate Negatives
Series 3. Backdrop Panels & Sign
Series 4. Artwork and Ephemera
Series 5. Publications
Acquisition Information
This collection was given by Wylie Wong to Stanford University, Special Collections in December 2013.
Related Collections
The Museum of Performance and Design, Performing Arts Library holds the "Collection of Chinese Theater Images in California" http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/kt8489q5fj
Scope and Contents
The collection contains photographs produced by May's Studio, including numerous portraits of actors and actresses who performed in San Francisco’s Chinatown during the 1920s-1930s. Included in the collection are a set of May's Studio glass-plate negatives and a set of painted panels used as backdrops in the studio. The collection also contains posters, artwork, and ephemera relating to theater, life, and culture in Chinatown during the early-mid 20th century.
Historical note
May's Studio was operated by Isabelle May Chan and Leo Chan in San Francisco’s Chinatown from 1923 to 1976. Leo Chan emigrated from China sometime after 1911. Isabelle was born in San Francisco. The Studio, which opened in Waverly Place, focused on producing publicity photographs for actors and actresses who performed in Chinatown theaters. Many of their photographs were of productions staged at the Great China Theater, which opened in 1925, and was later renamed the Great Star Theater. The Studio was also known for producing wedding portraits as well as photographing other aspects of life in Chinatown, including portraits of businesses, street life, parades, and other events. In 1931 the Studio moved to 770 Sacramento Street for the remainder of its operation. Wylie Wong is an Asian art and antiquities dealer based in San Francisco.
Chinatown (San Francisco, Calif.); May's Photo (Firm: San Francisco, Calif.); Operas, Chinese.; Studio Portraits; Photographs.; San Francisco (Calif.) -- Ephemera; Mei, Lanfang; Lee, Isabelle May; Wong, Wylie; Lee, Leo Chan
- Series 1. Photographs, The term "original print" is used to describe prints created by May's Studio through their original process. The term "copy prints" is used to describe prints which were made at a later date, probably during the 1980s or later. The date given for May's Studio copy prints is an estimate of when the original image was taken. If it was unclear when a print was produced, or if it appeared that a photograph was not associated with May's Studio, the more generic term "photographic print" was used.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains photographic prints produced by May's Studio, primarily during the 1920s-1930s. Photographs in this series include numerous portraits of actors and actresses in traditional Chinese theater costume as well as stage scenes from Chinese operas and other forms of performance. A number of the photographs of actors and actresses are large hand-colored portraits; some of these are embellished with glitter. Also in the series are other photographs by May's Studio, such as wedding albums, images of life in San Francisco's Chinatown, including special events, portraits of businesses and employees, street views, and building interiors. Some photographs are in panoramic formats. This series also contains some miscellaneous photographs not taken by May's Studio, such as more recent photographs of Chinese Opera performers. In addition to photographic prints, the series contains a small set of black and white negatives and color transparencies.
  - Actors and actresses in traditional Chinese theater costumes (original gelatin silver prints); some include May's Photo credit stamp, circa 1920s (Box 1, Folders 1-8)
  - Actors and actresses in traditional Chinese theater costumes (copy prints); some include May's Photo credit stamp; many of the original prints can be found in box 1 folders 1-8; circa 1920s (Box 2, Folders 1-33)
  - Actors and actresses in traditional Chinese theater costumes (copy prints); some include May's Photo credit stamp; many of the original prints can be found in box 1 folders 1-8; circa 1920s (Flat-box 5, Folders 8-14)
  - Actor in traditional Chinese theater costume (photographic print) circa 1920s (Flat-box 5, Folder 7)
  - California Historical Society archive sheets; used to evaluate material condition of loaned photographs for exhibition, "Chinese American Theater on the West Coast" 1983 (now in box 1 folders 1-8) (Box 1, Folders 14-15)
  - Mei Lanfang, portraits in costume from Farewell My Concubine and other performances (photographic prints), circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Mei Lanfang, portrait in tuxedo (copy print), circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mei Lanfang, portrait with three other men (copy print), circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mei Lanfang in "Heavenly Maid Scatters Flowers" (hand-colored photographic print mounted on Yung Cheong studio board), originally issued 1918 (Flat-box 6, Folder 1)
  - Mei Lanfang in "Heavenly Maid Scatters Flowers" (reproduction of hand-colored photograph), originally issued 1918 (Flat-box 6, Folder 2)
  - Mei Lanfang in "Heavenly Maid Scatters Flowers" (reproduction of hand-colored photograph), originally issued 1918 (Flat-box 11, Folder 1)
  - Portrait of an actor in traditional Chinese theater costume (original hand-colored photographic print, embellished with glitter), circa 1920s (Map-folder 41)
  - Portrait of an actress in traditional Chinese theater costume (original hand-colored photographic print, embellished with glitter), circa 1920s (Map-folder 43)
  - Portrait of an actor/actress in traditional Chinese theater costume (original hand-colored photographic print, embellished with glitter), circa 1920s (Map-folder 44)
  - Portrait of an actor/actress in traditional Chinese theater costume (original hand-colored photographic print, embellished with glitter), circa 1920s (Map-folder 45)
  - Portrait of an actor/actress in traditional Chinese theater costume (original hand-colored photographic print), circa 1920s (Map-folder 46)
  - Portrait of an actor in traditional Chinese theater costume (original hand-colored photographic print, embellished with glitter), circa 1920s (Map-folder 47)
  - Portrait of an actor in traditional Chinese theater costume (original photographic print), circa 1920s (Map-folder 49)
  - Portrait of an actress with a parasol (original hand-colored photographic print), circa 1920s (Map-folder 42)
  - Portrait of an actress with a parasol (reproduction of hand-colored photograph), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Portrait of an actress with a parasol (reproduction of hand-colored photograph), circa 1920s (Flat-box 11, Folder 2)
  - Portrait of an actress, seated in black dress (original hand-colored photographic print), circa 1920s (Map-folder 48)
  - Portrait of an actress, seated in black dress (reproduction of hand-colored photograph), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Portrait of an actress, seated in black dress (reproduction of hand-colored photograph), circa 1920s (Flat-box 11, Folder 3)
  - Portrait of Gee Lan Niu (copy print), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Portrait of an actor in the role of a Hua Dan (original print), circa 1920s (Flat-box 12, Folder 1)
  - Group portrait, actors and actresses in club house (copy print) (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Group portrait, actors and actresses (copy print), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Group portrait, women/actresses (copy print) (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Stage scene and cast of actors in traditional Chinese theater costume (original prints), circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Scenes from traditional Chinese theater productions (original prints); some include May's Photo credit stamp; productions were probably staged at the Great China Theater (later the Great Star Theater), circa 1920s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Scenes from traditional Chinese theater productions; also includes patriotic political plays, including play on Sun Yat-Sen and the Chinese Republican era (copy prints); some include May's Photo credit stamp; productions were probably staged at the Great China Theater (later the Great Star Theater), circa 1920s (Box 3, Folders 1-33)
  - Scenes from traditional Chinese theater productions (copy prints); some include May's Photo credit stamp; productions were probably staged at the Great China Theater (later the Great Star Theater), circa 1920s (Flat-box 5, Folders 2-6)
  - Scene from traditional Chinese theater production (original print); probably staged at the Great China Theater (later the Great Star Theater), circa 1920s (Flat-box 10, Folder 1)
  - Scene from traditional Chinese theater production (photographic print mounted on board), circa 1920s (Flat-box 5, Folder 1)
  - Theater scene (photographic print mounted on board), circa 1920s (Flat-box 11, Folder 4)
  - Illustrations of traditional Chinese theater (copy prints) (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Miscellaneous black and white negatives (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Transparencies of hand colored portraits of actors/actresses, others (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Great China Theater, inaugural photograph (copy print), 1925 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Chinatown lobby/bar (original prints), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Chinatown parade, marching band (original and copy prints), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Chinatown parade, dragon (original and copy prints), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Chinatown parade, group portrait in costume (original and copy prints), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Chinatown parade, float with women in costume (original and copy prints), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Chinatown street view with Shanghai Low cafe (original and copy prints), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Banquet at Shanghai Low cafe for Yellow Cab Company, 1928 (photographic print) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Chinatown, exterior of Hop Sing Tong building decorated for a convention (original print), circa 1920s (Flat-box 11, Folder 6)
  - Chinatown, interior of a store with staff (original print), circa 1920s (Flat-box 11, Folder 7)
  - Chinatown, interior of a store with staff (photographic print mounted on board), circa 1920s (Flat-box 11, Folder 8)
  - Portrait of large group in front of Wing Fung and Co. (copy print), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Royal China Theater stage (copy print) circa 1880s (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - General Tsaiting Kai, welcome celebration (original print), circa 1930s (Flat-box 12, Folder 2)
  - General Tsaiting Kai, welcome celebration (copy print), circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - General Tsaiting Kai, welcome celebration (copy print of panoramic photograph), circa 1930s (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - General Tsaiting Kai, welcome celebration; pictures youth groups and other groups in front the grandstand (original panoramic photographic print), circa 1930s (Map-folder 40)
  - Group portrait at an event with Republic of China flag (original print), circa 1920s (Flat-box 11, Folder 9)
  - Group portrait with Republic of China flag; includes May's Studio photo stamp (copy print) (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Group portrait with Republic of China flag; includes May's Studio photo stamp (copy print), circa 1920s (Flat-box 6, Folder 12)
  - Panoramic photograph of group portrait aboard S.S. Guatemala, with Republic of China flag (original print), circa 1920s (Flat-box 13, Folder 4)
  - Group portrait aboard S.S. Guatemala, with Republic of China flag (copy print of panoramic photograph), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Group portrait (copy print) (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Group portrait in front of National Herbal Institute of China (original and copy print), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Interior of National Herbal Institute of China (original print), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Exterior of National Herbal Institute of China (original print), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Group portrait in front of May's Studio (original and copy print), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Exterior of China Emporium (original and copy print), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Interior of Chinatown store (copy print) circa 1890 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Interior of Chinatown store (original and copy print), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Exterior of Chinatown store (original and copy print), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Kwong Hong Fat and Co. Importers; interior and exterior views with portraits of staff (original and copy prints) circa 1920s (Flat-box 6, Folders 3-4)
  - Portrait of a woman and interior (photographic print) (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Portrait of a woman/actress (original print); includes May’s Studio original enclosure, circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Portrait of two men/actors (copy print) (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Portrait of a man (original print), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Portrait of two men (original print), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Portrait of two men (original and copy print), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Portrait of a boy with flowers (original and copy print; original partially colored), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Portrait of a group of men in front of a building (photographic print), circa 1920s (Flat-box 6, Folder 6)
  - Group portrait (copy print) (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Portrait of group of women/actresses (partially colored photographic print), circa 1920s (Flat-box 6, Folder 5)
  - Portrait of a young boy with Christmas tree and ornaments (copy print), circa 1920s (Flat-box 6, Folder 7)
  - Portrait of a boy in traditional clothes (copy print), circa 1920s (Flat-box 6, Folder 8)
  - Portrait of a man in traditional clothes (copy print), circa 1920s (Flat-box 6, Folder 9)
  - Portrait of seated men in traditional dress; includes May's Photo stamp (original print), circa 1920s (Flat-box 12, Folder 4)
  - Portrait of seated men in modern dress; May's Photo stamp (original print), circa 1920s (Flat-box 12, Folder 5)
  - Portrait of a man and woman (original hand-colored photographic print), circa 1920s (Flat-box 50, Folder 1)
  - Family portrait (copy print) circa 1920s (Flat-box 6, Folder 10)
  - Portrait of Calvin Chin and Anthony Wong, Medical Corps commissioned officers (copy print) (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Postcard portraits, circa 1920s (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Photograph of framed poster showing officers of the San Francisco Lodge, Chinese American Citizens Alliance, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - "Mandarin with a bodyguard" (copy print) circa 1904 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Lumber camp (copy print) circa 1880s (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Chinese Telephone Exchange (copy print), circa 1895 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Tye Leung (copy print), circa 1912 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Chinese priest in traditional robe (copy print) (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - May's Studio, pornography (photographic prints) (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Interior room (photographic print),circa 1920s (Flat-box 6, Folder 11)
  - Photograph of poster for play The First Born circa 1920s (Flat-box 6, Folder 13)
  - Photograph of war atrocity (copy print) (Flat-box 6, Folder 14)
  - Wedding photographs from album (original prints), circa 1920s (Box 4, Folders 48-50)
  - Wedding portrait (photographic print mounted on board), circa 1920s (Flat-box 11, Folder 5)
  - Photograph album; includes wedding photos; other events; organization, group, and individual portraits; also objects and Chinatown buildings/street views; some with May's Photo stamp (original prints), circa 1920s, Album leaves were found loose and have been foldered individually; photos are usually mounted on both sides of leaves. (Flat-box 7, Folders 1-37)
  - Photograph album; includes wedding photos; other events; organization, group, and individual portraits; also objects and Chinatown buildings/street views; some with May's Photo stamp (original prints), circa 1920s, Album leaves were found loose and have been foldered individually; photos are usually mounted on both sides of leaves. (Flat-box 8, Folders 1-28)
  - Photograph album; includes wedding photos; other events; organization, group, and individual portraits; also objects and Chinatown buildings/street views; some with May's Photo stamp (original prints), circa 1920s, Album leaves were found loose and have been foldered individually; photos are usually mounted on both sides of leaves. (Flat-box 9, Folders 1-23)
  - Photograph album; includes wedding photos; other events; organization, group, and individual portraits; also objects and Chinatown buildings/street views; some with May's Photo stamp (original prints), circa 1920s, Album leaves were found loose and have been foldered individually; photos are usually mounted on both sides of leaves. (Flat-box 10, Folders 2-30)
  - Portrait of large group in front of Wing Fung and Co. (original print), circa 1920s (Flat-box 12, Folder 3)
  - Panoramic photograph with five inset photos of actresses (original print), circa 1920 (Flat-box 13, Folder 1)
  - Panoramic photograph with five inset photos of actresses (original print), circa 1920 (Flat-box 13, Folder 2)
  - Panoramic photograph with five inset photos of a young girl (original print), circa 1920 (Flat-box 13, Folder 3)
  - Actors in costume from the play Princess Cheung Ping (photographic prints), 2001 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Actors in costume from the play Lioness Roars (photographic prints), 2003 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Portrait of Marlene Dietrich (photographic print), 1937 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Traditional Japanese body tattoo (photographic print) (Box 4, Folder 52)
- Series 2. Glass-Plate Negatives
  This series contains a set of glass-plate negatives from May's Studio. Most are images of actors, actresses, and theater scenes. A few of the plates contain other types of portraits and subject matter.
  Restricted Material
  All of the images on the glass-plate negatives are represented as prints in Series 1. The plates are fragile, so access is partially restricted. Please inquire at the Department of Special Collections if you have a particular need to examine the glass-plate negatives.
  - Actors and actresses in traditional Chinese theater costumes (glass-plate negatives) (Box 18, Items 1-10)
  - Actors and actresses in traditional Chinese theater costumes (glass plate negatives) (Box 19, Items 1-10)
  - Actors and actresses in traditional Chinese theater costumes (glass plate negatives) (Box 20, Items 1-10)
  - Actors and actresses in traditional Chinese theater costumes (glass plate negatives), Items 7-8 are two pieces of one broken plate. (Box 21, Items 1-8)
  - Actors and actresses in traditional Chinese theater costumes (glass plate negatives) (Box 22, Items 1-10)
- Series 3. Backdrop Panels & Sign
  This series contains a set of backdrop panels and the studio's sign. The panels are made of painted canvas on board. They contain imagery painted in a traditional Chinese style and depict scenes from mythological stories and operas as well as animals. The panels were used as backdrops for portraits in May’s studio and also possibly utilized in stage sets.
  - May's Photo Studio backdrop panel; interior scene with a man and a woman embracing (painted canvas on board) (Oversize-box 51)
  - May's Photo Studio backdrop panel; woman in a garden (painted canvas on board) (Oversize-box 52)
  - May's Photo Studio backdrop panel; mythological scene with multiple figures in the clouds (painted canvas on board) (Oversize-box 53)
  - May's Photo Studio backdrop panel; interior scene with a man and a woman and views towards the outside landscape (painted canvas on board) (Oversize-box 54)
  - May's Photo Studio backdrop panel; rooster (painted canvas on board) (Oversize-box 55)
  - May's Photo Studio backdrop panel; mythological scene with two women (painted canvas on board) (Oversize-box 56)
  - May's Photo Studio backdrop panel; crane (painted canvas on board) (Oversize-box 57)
  - May's Photo Studio sign (Oversize-box 58)
    Chinese characters carved in relief on both sides of wooden panel, with paint.
- Series 4. Artwork and Ephemera
  This series contains prints, posters, ephemera, and artwork. Printed material includes a set of Chinese opera publicity prints, produced in Hong Kong and Shanghai in the 1930s. Examples of other items include a souvenir booklet commemorating Mei Lanfang's US tour and an advertisement for Remy Martin cognac, printed in Hong Kong in the 1950s and featuring a Chinese opera scene. Later materials include other Chinese opera publicity materials as well as posters and pamphlets for a "Pear Garden in the West"--a 1980s celebration of the history of Chinese theater in America.
  - Chinese opera print (visual work); Yu Tang Chun, Story of Su San; printed by k and K printing co., Shanghai, circa 1930s (Flat-box 13, Folder 5)
  - Chinese opera print (visual work); actor/actress; K. and K. Printing, Shanghai, circa 1930s (Map-folder 23)
  - Chinese opera print (visual work); Hang Zhiying, "Lady in a Garden"; K. and K. Printing, Shanghai, circa 1930s (Map-folder 24)
  - Chinese opera print (visual work); Mei Lanfang, role of White Snake, circa 1930s (Map-folder 25)
  - Chinese opera print (visual work); two scenes; Zee Shin Kee Offset Printing, Shanghai, circa 1930s (Map-folder 26)
  - Chinese opera print (visual work); two scenes; Zee Shin Kee Offset Printing, Shanghai, circa 1930s (Map-folder 27)
  - Chinese opera print (visual work); actor/actress, circa 1930s (Map-folder 28)
  - Chinese opera print (visual work); actor/actress, circa 1930s (Map-folder 29)
  - Chinese opera print (visual work); actor/actress circa 1930s (Map-folder 30)
  - Chinese opera print (visual work); two scenes; Zee Shin Kee Offset Printing, Shanghai, circa 1930s (Map-folder 31)
  - Chinese opera print (visual work); actor/actress in winter scene, circa 1930s (Map-folder 32)
  - Chinese print (visual work); woman in a garden pavilion, circa 1930s (Flat-box 13, Folder 6)
  - Chinese print (visual work); ducks in a pond (Flat-box 14, Folder 2)
  - Chinese New Year prints (visual work); opera/story scenes; printed in Shanghai (Flat-box 16, Folders 1-4)
  - Chinese New Year Print (visual work); lion (Flat-box 16, Folder 5)
  - Print (visual work); mythological scenes from opera/operas; Li Shan Pictures Co., House No. 12, Shanghai (printed in Hong Kong), circa 1930s (Map-folder 33)
  - Lion print (visual work), circa 1930s (Map-folder 34)
  - Map of China during World War II; advertising poster for C.T. Sun and Son with images of products; map shows regions occupied by Japanese forces and the Chinese National Government (Map-folder 36)
  - Portrait print (visual work) of a woman/actress in contemporary dress (mounted on cardboard), circa 1930s (Map-folder 35)
  - Mei Lanfang, souvenir booklet; contains photographs, circa 1930 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Remy Martin cognac poster; printed in Hong Kong, circa 1950 (Flat-box 16, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous water color painting (Flat-box 14, Folder 1)
  - View of San Francisco Chinatown street, print (visual work) (Flat-box 14, Folder 3)
  - View of Japanese Tea Garden, Golden Gate Park, print (visual work) (Flat-box 14, Folder 4)
  - Chinese news clippings with photograph of beauty pageant contestant (Flat-box 14, Folder 5)